This motion picutre is an adaptation of the real life story of a historic figure.
Although artistic license has been taken, the essence of the story remains true...
...to the events that continue to inspire generations.
It remains one of the oldest accounts of humanity's struggle equality & freedom.
Bilal
Inspired by a true story
A film by : Ayman Jamal
Enjoy!
Translation and synchronizing
Ikraam
BILAL: Ghufaira!
MOTHER: Ah, ah, ah...
Oh!
Mother, who are they?
Mother!
Keep your sister safe, Bilal.
No!
GHUFAIRA: Bilal.
Are you alright?
- I am fine.
- Was it... that dream again ?
Here.
I was saving this for you.
- There's a piece of it missing.
- Well, I'm waiting.
- Oh, (chuckles) why thank you my wonderful
amazing, sister.
- You are very welcome my loving brother.
That is more like it.
- What can one Dirham (sliver piece) buy?
- Well, to start...
...a blessing! From one of the Gods!
Maybe one of them will bring you
something to stop your nightmares.
- Where were these Gods when Mother
needed them?
I will buy you something sweet to eat instead. (BANG)
GUARD: Ghufaira, fetch water for the master!
Move it!
I'll get it.
(shouts in the markets)
(yells) Spices, spices!
(more shouts)
Different colours, different prices.
How much it has been?
(metals clanging)
(offers) Would you like to taste one?
OKBA: Idols for sale!
Idols for sale!
They come in all colors and shapes!
And make your wishes comes true!
Idols for fame!
Idols for strength!
Idols for fertility!
Idols for beauty!
I can see that you definitely don't
need an idol for beauty.
The idol needs you. (laughs)
- Thank you.
- But, for fertility!
You want to bear a son, don't you?
With this, you can bear triplets! (laughs)
(camels grunt)
(shouts in the markets) Sweets!
(people greeting) Good morning, my brother!
(warns) Watch where you going boy!
(shouts from afar)
CHARLATAN PRIEST: The idols see all!
The idols know all!
Stray not into the desert sands!
Lest the harsh flames of wrath consume you!
Come, enter!
Prove your faith with wealth and gifts!
Appease the idols and Gods...
Or else...
(deep whispers)
Come, boy!
Come!
You wish to be free of nightmares...
Don't you?
Take that coin from your pocket...
(deep whispers)
No offering too small...
No wish too big...
You can have...
...whatever you desire!
The idols see all...
(panting & mumbling)
SIDEKICK: You missed!
SAFWAN: On purpose.
My arrows need worthy target.
I wouldn't waste them on a chicken.
But a deer...
Where would we find a deer?
What?
S-safwan, what are you doing?
Safwan!
There's a deer...
...a black one.
Over here, slave!
I said, come here!
Stop, slave!
I command you!
(chuckles) The deer thinks it's a lion.
- Yeah, you better watch out! (growls)
- You, better watch out!
- Aa-I was kidding.
- Shut up!
Now, get her.
GHUFAIRA: Let go!
- Don't move.
- Don't, please don't!
BILAL: No!
(laughs) Safwan, looks like
you got your deer...
...in his tail!
- You will not harm her !
- How dare you give me an order?
Teach this rat a lesson!
GHUFAIRA: Please forgive him
master Safwan!
IDOL MAKER: Hey, what are you
boys doing?
Oh, I-I didn't know it was you,
young master Safwan.
Apologies.
Are these slaves bothering you?
I'll thrash them, if they are!
Come on, let's go.
- Tell your father, I'll deliver his
order today!
BILAL: Ghufaira!
Did they hurt you? Oh...
I should have been here to protect you.
I will never let anyone hurt you
ever again.
BLACK MARKET MERCHANT:
Step forward! Patience!
(competing shouts)
Make your offer.
And this prized specimen shall
be yours!
Do i hear 2nd on that?
3rd? Sold, sold!
Get this wretch out of here!
OKBA: This is the finest slave in
my possession
He's clever, he reads and writes!
He speaks twenty languages.
Twenty i say! (laughs)
(snake hissing)
He even speaks to animals!
Oh, great Umayya!
You can't ask for a better servant
on your trading missions, oh no...
Ah! That one is not quite as clever...
...but he is as strong as rocks!
UMAYYA: I'll take him.
- You will?
I-I-I mean, e-excellent choice!
He's a bit expensive, but I know
the gods has been generous to you...
...my dearest Umayya!
- Okba...
...one of these days, I'm gonna dip
your tongue in a bowl of dry sand.
Have him delivered.
- Oh, thank you, thank you, thank you!
Thank you! (laughs)
Ah! Blessed Umayya! (laughs)
Gracious! Magnificent! (laughs)
IDOL MAKER: Your honor!
I have the Idols you ordered.
Should I bring them to your home
or the shop at the market ?
-What do you think ?
The market you idiot!
And the next time you are late...
...I won't pay.
- A thousand pardons.
It won't happen again!
I-I was delayed. I-I had to come to
the aid of your son...
...Safwan!
- Hmm? What about Safwan?
- He was being assaulted, by
a slave boy!
- Which slave ?
- They called him Bilal.
He-he had your son on the ground!
But I, I pull him up.
Saved him from a thrashing!
- Enough!
Take these idols to my store at once...
...or forget the deal.
- Yes sir, of course!
Right away.
UMAYYA: Bilal!
Pick it up.
I said, pick it up.
Whose apple is this?
Whose is it?
BILAL: Yours sir, yours.
- And what is the difference
between you and this apple?
- No difference, sir.
(grunts)
- Don't you forget it again.
Take him out to the courtyard...
...and whip him.
GUARD: Move!
SAFWAN: No matter what you do...
...a master breeds a master...
...and a slave breeds a slave.
Father, I hope you're going to teach him
a lesson he'll never...
- How could you let a slave beat you?
- Bilal's lying, father!
The slave is lying.
He did not beat... (smacks)
- You make me look like a fool.
Stop it!
Stop it I say!
Listen.
He's isn't crying...
...and you shouldn't be crying either.
I dont care what happened...
...don't ever let a slave embarrass
me in public, again.
(whips)
BILAL: Mother, what kind of man
was my father?
MOTHER: Your father was a great man.
What do you want to be when
you grow up Bilal?
A farmer?
Or may be a merchant that makes
a lot of money?
- Ha! I want to be a great warrior!
(laughs) - And that's what you will be,
a great warrior.
With a beautiful voice.
- And I want to ride a big horse.
And I will fight enemies...
...and protect you, and Ghufaira.
- That's very honourable, Bilal.
But, remember...
...a sword and a horse...
...cannot make you a great man.
- They can't?
- No.
Being a great man,
...means living without chains
- Huh, chains?
- No, (chuckles) the ones you can't see...
...the ones in here.
- Inside me?
- Being a warrior,
...wont make you a great man,
...if you are chained to anger
and vengeance.
Superstition and fear are chains too,
...and there are others.
To be a great man,
...you have to break free of them all.
- But how I do I do that?
I can't see inside me.
- I can...
...and I see the heart of a great man, Bilal.
You'll find the way. Guidance will come.
You'll see.
No chains will hold to you.
No chains...
BILAL: You were wrong, mother.
I am a slave.
And I will always be in chain.
GHUFAIRA: (gasps) Why did they have
to whip you?
You didn't do anything!
- It does not matter.
Master Umayya can do whatever he
wants with us.
- Bilal!
Look at what I found.
I know you didn't mean to lose this!
You can still use it to make an offering.
I heard the Priest said;
"Big blessing can come from small gifts."
- I don't need it.
I am never gonna hope for anything again.
I am a Slave!
And no God in the market has the power
to change that!
- Alright. I'll keep it.
And i won't spend it either.
It's yours.
I'll keep it safe for you until
you ask for it back.
BILAL: Very funny!
BILAL: No, no, no!
SAAD: (laughs) The way you fly off
that horse...
...amazes me every single time.
It never gets old!
- (laughs) It's only been twice...
...today!
- I, on the other hand...
...never miss.
- You just love to show off,
don't you Saad?
Besides, you have all the time and
money to practice.
- You need more than money to
be the best of what you do.
You need a great deal of determination.
- Ha, right !
So your determination is to hunt fruit?
I have to get back.
Believe me,
...you do not want to upset
master Umayya.
- Tell me something, Bilal.
Why don't you just start riding
and keep on going?
Cross those dunes to whatever
they may lead?
- And find my palace?
More likely I'd find it...
...only to end up working in it.
See you later, 'Apple hunter'.
SAAD: Here, for your troubles.
Till next time, my friend.
CHILD: Please, get a little bit of coin ?
Please, I want some food, some coins.
Please? (sighs)
Please, some coins?
- MAN: Out of the way child!
- Please, I have no food.
(sighs)
295.1
BILAL: No...
...you do not want to do that.
- But I'm so hungry.
- Here,
...take this.
- You're so kind.
AL-SIDDIQ: You would rather pay for your
own pocket than to see this god losing wealth?
- I wanted to spare the boy a beating.
- Ah, then you care more for a beggar boy...
...than an idol?
Don't you believe
the promises of the priest?
- My apologies, sir.
I am just a slave.
I know no better.
- Don't you?
Or do you?
- You're no priest.
You're... the lord of merchants.
Al-Sadiq! (Abu Bakr)
- Indeed.
Are you kneeling because you thought
I was a priest?
Or was it my question that
frightened you ?
Get up son, do not be afraid.
- (chuckles) No, sir I'm not frightened.
- You seem amused?
- Your honor, what do you know about fear?
- I have seen enough of it in the eyes of the
people.
Enough to understand what make slaves of
the many.
A woman is afraid she will bear a girl...
...she pays an offering and begs...
...to idols to fix it.
A rich man fears poverty...
...he shares a little
of his money with the Gods...
...and promises more if they
help him to stay wealthy.
An old man fears death...
...so he pays a priest for deliverance.
This fear compells them to seek
refuge in these Gods.
Gods of greed, of injustice...
...with hope that all their problems will go away.
Surely the sacred structure was not built
to house for all of this corruption.
It was built...
...so that all mankind could stand together...
...as equals...
...and follow the One Creator.
- Except for slaves.
- Son...
...no one is born a slave.
You were free once...
...were you not?
- I was, once...
...a long time ago.
Devils raided my village...
...destroyed my home.
They took me, and Ghufaira...
...my sister.
- What about your...
- She still talks to me.
Sir...
...all this talk of equality...
...is wishful thinking.
It holds no meaning to me.
So save your speech for a man
who can afford this...
...thing you are selling.
- Young man!
Life is more generous than you may think.
I am not here to sell you anything.
- It maybe sir...
...but not for slaves.
My master is expecting this.
I must return.
-Whom do you serve?
- Master Umayya.
The greatest man in the city.
- And what is your name, son?
- Bilal.
- Bilal!
I saw greatness in the hand
that saved that boy today.
And remember...
...great men are those who have...
...the will to choose their own destiny.
GUARD: Yalla (let's go), hurry up!
Hurry up, move it!
Right now, faster!
(whips)
(screams)
SOLDIER: Good job, sir.
Sir?
BILAL: Master Safwan!
Master Safwan...
...your father summons you.
SAFWAN: How many times do I have to remind you?
Kneel when you come before me, slave.
Kneel!
Few were born to rule...
...others, to serve.
SOHEIB: You do not look good on your knees, brother.
Get up my friend!
You need to see what I got
for the feast tonight...
...you will love it!
GHUFAIRA: Where is he?
You are late!
- (chuckles) You remember my sister...
...Ghufaira?
- My lady...
I am Soheib.
A first grade Slave...
...and blacksmith extraordinare.
- (chuckles) Yes, a funny man.
- Where were you?
It almost time for the feast.
They will whip you if you are late.
No way.
The master told me to fetch Safwan.
- Did he harm you?
- I would've turned this Safwan into
a sac of potatoes...
...if I'd only got there sooner.
That princess!
He and that little goon who follows
him.
You must remain strong, Bilal.
They are only as strong as
the fear they put inside us.
We must never give in.
- (chuckles) Alright, back to work.
- Behold...
...special delivery...
...to your master from my master.
- (gasps) That's very shiny!
- Hmm, nice work Soheib.
- (chuckles) Yes, it's my finest one yet.
MAN: That's right, it's
out sadiq (friend).
I cannot believe!
This man goes about us, speaking
against the Gods.
Every day!
How many followed him,
I do not know.
ABU AL-HAKAM: You leave too
much exposed.
You relied too much on luck.
UMAYYA: Luck favors the bold.
- Perhaps.
But are you willing to risk it at
the real world?
- You ask as if you dont know me.
- I ask...
...because I see a threat looming.
- You are truly obsessed with this nonsense.
- This nonsense can strike you
where you stand, Umayya!
Let's makes an example out of them...
...a reminder to those who
dare stand against us!
After all,
we have a business to take care of.
- Abu Al-Hakam! As always, you've managed...
...to ruin my evening with your concerns.
Bilal!
Come, sing for us!
Let's lighten the mood.
OKBA: Ah, yes! I-I have heard my slaves speaking
of the...
...swirlest voice.
Lets hear it!
# Distant shadows, #
# Mountains and trees. #
# Here I stand, #
# As she shelters me. #
# Distant shadows, #
# As dark as night. #
# The sky cries to us all, #
# As it sends down its tears. #
# Here I stand, #
# As she shelters me. #
# Distant shadows, #
# Mother, please hide. #
# They draw so near, #
# Oh, these shadows. #
# Why are they so close, #
# As the sky sends down, #
#  Its tears. #
(distant chatters) Look at him crying!
(distant shouts) Sing one more song!
ABU AL-HAKAM: Blasphemy!
Blasphemy!
Sinners! (whips)
Blasphemers!
GUARD: What are you looking at?
Eyes down, slave!
- You quench your thirst from the
waters that our Gods has provided you...
...yet what do you offer in return? Huh?
Nothing!
Today you repent to your
sins to me, traitors!
BILAL: No! Soheib!
Let him go!
Cowards!
No!
GUARD: Get this one!
Whip him! (whips)
- Please, stop!
(horse grunts)
GUARD: Please!
PEOPLE:  Look, it's him!
- It's the Lion!
PEOPLE: It's the great warrior!
- It is Hamza!
GUARD: Abu Al-Hakam, it's the Lion!
- Hamza! You've arrived just in time.
Look at these dogs!
These sinners!
They must be disciplined and so does... (smacks)
HAMZA: And so does who, coward?
You call yourselves men?
You're a disgrace to Mecca and to
your forefathers!
Since when were these waters weren't free for all?
And know this,
...I only see God through the actions of men.
Your savagery today uncover
the true color of your belief.
So fight me...!
...or get out of my sight!
AL-SIDDIQ: Hamza!
You arrived just in time, old friend.
- Al-Siddiq! (Abu Bakr)
It has been too long.
- Come, we have much to talk about.
SAAD: Come on Bilal, help me get him up.
509.1
HAMZA: My people, take as much as you need from
the Zamzam well, no soldier will stop you.
BILAL: Do you believe change will come?
Even for us?
GHUFAIRA: Maybe.
Mother believed so.
Why are you asking?
Bilal?
- This morning...
...I went to see him again.
AL-SIDDIQ: And who could this be?
There are no young thieves to save
out here.
BILAL: Sir...
...what did you mean before...
...that we choose?
Are you offering to buy me?
- (laughs) Would you like me to?
- Well, you seem like a better master
than the one I serve now.
- Believe it or not, Bilal...
...your master is a slave himself.
- Hmm. Really?
And who is his master?
- Greed...
...the worst of them all.
- Are you saying that no one is ever free?
- I am not.
- And how would I ever be free?
- Only you can enslave yourself, Bilal.
- I-I apologize...
...I just...
...I have never been treated with
such kindness before...
...and I-I still... I don't understand.
Why a noble like you would want...
...to help someone like me?
Is there something you expect me
to do in return?
- You see, Bilal...
...this man (the Prophet Muhammad PBUH)
once guided me when I was truly lost.
A greater noble man...
...who spreads the message of equality.
I have chosen to do the same,
...so here we stand.
And who knows, Bilal...
...perhaps one day , you'll inspire
the hearts of many as well.
- Me?
How can I do that?
- Come, sit.
You sought me out to talk to me,
didn't you?
Let's talk.
GHUFAIRA: So... our mother was right.
BILAL: Yes...
...she was.
- It always seemed that way.
She was always so very wise.
UMAYYA: A toast to my son, Safwan!
He had the business sense to make a killing
on those little idols. (cheers)
Now he can afford
to host his first feast. (cheers)
(toasting) To Safwan!
(chatters)
Are you still sulking because you
passed up a good deal?
I told you these portable idols would sell.
ABU AL-HAKAM: It may be the last money any of us ever make.
- What are you taking about?
There a fortune in these little idols!
Should have heard the priest hawking
them in today the market.
- You were not there later.
There was a dispute...
...and people listened.
- A dispute?
Who created this dispute?
- Wolves, from the new Movement.
(the Prophet Muhammad PBUH)
Their reputation is spreading like
wildfire across the city!
- Oh, not this business again. If you
tell me there is an army coming...
...I'll worry.
- What about the talk of freedom?
Do you worry about that?
- What are you talking about?
- They say we are praying on the people's
desperation.
They say that a real God
would never ask for a man's fortune.
What happens to our business...
...if this message takes hold?
- And how long do you think the other merchants
will tolerate such a message?
They will soon be laughed out of town...
...or someone will strike a deal with them.
You'll see.
Look around!
There is only one God...
...and it is money.
That is the true faith of this city.
- Well these days, not all our
merchant are worshipping the idols.
- Where is that lazy one
who used to sell idols in sacks?
- He joined the Movement the other day.
- (grunts) And what about the
Lord of Merchants, where is he?
- Oh, joined them too.
A long time ago.
OKBA: Abu Al-Hakam is right.
People still buy my date idols...
..but I think they're eating them for desserts.
- Are there any other traitors in my house?
Well?
Stand, and reveal yourselves!
SAFWAN: Maybe you should ask your slave?
- What? What are you talking about ?
- (sighs) Slave?
Why don't you tell my father
about your new-found friend?
- Impossible!
You must be mistaken.
There are no traitors in my household.
Right, Bilal?
Speak up!
Safwan has accused you something.
What do you have to say for yourself?
I said speak up, slave!
You have my permission to talk!
BILAL: We are - all born equals.
We breathe the same air...
...we bleed the same color...
...and we'll die... and be buried...
...beneath the same ground.
I believe... I am as free a man...
... as you are.
- Free? Equal?
I hate these words.
Umayya, this one woke up on the wrong side
of the ground today. (chuckles)
Free? Equals huh?
Everyone! Look here!
We are both equals!
- You once slapped my face because I let this slave
make a fool of you.
What are you going to do now, Father?
- Guards!
MOTHER: *Being a great man begins with
taking off your chains.*
GUARD: Quickly slave, move it!
(door slams)
Bind him! Renounce your claim!
Renounce!
UMAYYA: Crush his spirit.
Let him rot inside the cage.
No water...
...no food.
He'll come back.
SAAD: Bilal, hang in there...
...I will bring help.
MOTHER: *I see the heart of a great man, Bilal.*
GUARD: Renounce your claim!
No one is to touch this slave! Umayya's orders!
Renounce your claim, slave!
BILAL: I will not!
(screams)
GHUFAIRA: Bilal, are you alright?
SAAD: You have to be strong, Bilal.
SAFWAN: A master breeds a master...
...and a slave breeds a slave.
AS-SIDDIQ: *All humanity is a single nation...*
GHUFAIRA: Bilal, are you alright?
*...for those who look outside...*
*...only dream.*
MOTHER: *Guidance will come, you'll see.*
UMAYYA: And what is the difference
between you and this apple?
(whispers) Renounce your claim...
SAFWAN: Kneel when you come before me, slave!
AL-SIDDIQ: *And those who look within...
are awakened.*
*When you are awakened...*
*...your story will race out of this desert...*
*...across the world...*
*...where great men are tested.*
*Prepare yourself, Bilal.*
MOTHER: *Being a great man...
means living without chains.*
UMAYYA: Bilal, are you awake?
Good.
You're braver than I thought.
I take credit for that.
It comes from watching me all these
years, I'm sure.
(whispers) Why don't you just die?
It took guts to reveal yourself like that...
...but sadly, you still think like a slave.
I'll get you back on track
with a little secret. See...
...I never believed in these Gods.
No, no, no, no. I'm not a fool.
The truth is... we are both slaves, Bilal.
The difference between us...
...is I worship whatever empowers me.
You...
...worship something that will destroy you.
A free man would have sought out the profit
in this situation.
For example a free man might offer
to spy on his master's enemies.
He might realize the advantage in that.
Do you understand what I'm saying, Bilal ?
Get him some water.
Should i take off these chains?
What do you say, Bilal?
- My chains...
...are already off.
- That's funny...
...because I see them.
Or does your invisible God make other
things invisible too?
- I'm talking about the chains...
...in here.
- Stop talking in riddles!
Do you know how much trouble you're in?
I can have you killed right now.
- It doesn't matter what you do to me...
...and there's nothing you can give me.
I am... already free.
- And what about your sister?
Is she free too?
So, are you going to consider my
proposition or not?
You wanted a horse?
I will give you two.
And I will provide both you and your
sister, a home.
(whispers) Accept his offer!
(shouts outside) Bring him out here! Bring him!
- Bring him out!
(shouts outside) Let him go!
- This is why you are a slave while I am rich!
You don't recognize when you've
been given an opportunity.
Too bad.
- Then, kill me.
- I'm not going to kill you.
Yet, you might still die.
GUARD: Your time has come.
SAAD: No, Bilal!
CHARLATAN PRIEST: Tell me, slave.
Who are you going to?
Is He stronger than I am?
Is He stronger than my Gods?
For with their power...
...and mine...
...I can have you killed...
...or set free.
This....
...is my God.
Do you want it to come to your aid?
Accept...
...and I will ask it to absolve you
of your sins.
AS-SIDDIQ: I've already offered a fair price for him.
UMAYYA: Very fair.
- Then what is the reason for bringing him out here?
(shouts) Crush him!
- If you injure him...
...then he is of no value to me...
...and the deal is off.
- We'll see.
CHARLATAN PRIEST: This slave
has been charged with the most heinous of crimes!
He stands against his masters!
For this offense...
...he will be punished!
GHUFAIRA: No!
You will kill him!
Please! No! Stop!
(grunts)
GHUFAIRA: He will die, Safwan!
Please, no!
SAFWAN: Feel that...
...slave?
Give up, Bilal.
You can end this.
Cry for forgiveness...
...and accept us as your real masters.
And these....
...as your true Gods!
How many Gods are there?
Can you count...
...slave?
- One...
...only One!
CHARLATAN PRIEST: It can't be!
SAFWAN: You are a fool!
BILAL: I... am...
...free.
GHUFAIRA: No, no, Bilal!
Please, stop!
He will die!
AL-SIDDIQ: I will double the offer.
UMAYYA: I think you've lost your head for business.
Sold!
Remove the stone.
SAAD: Bilal?
- I would've given all I own for him.
- For a slave?
- No.
For a brother.
- Don't tell me that this new Movement...
...makes slaves and nobles brothers!
- It does.
SAAD: Easy, easy.
- Bilal? Talk to me.
- His sister!
I'll pay the same for her!
- You're asking the wrong person.
I gave it to Safwan as a gift.
SAFWAN: I won't sell her...
...not even for your whole business.
Take her!
GHUFAIRA: No!
AL-SIDDIQ: What is the meaning of this?
Unhand her!
- Bilal!
799.1
BILAL: Ghufaira!
Three months later...
BILAL: I will forever be grateful...
...for you have saved my life.
AL-SIDDIQ: To save one life, my brother...
...is like saving all humanity.
SAAD: So how does it feel to walk the
streets of Mecca...
...as a free man?
- (sighs) It feels good just to be walking.
Where's Soheib?
- With Hamza...
...and the Lord of Merchants (Al-Siddiq).
They wait for us at the gate.
AL-SIDDIQ: Word of your defiance makes its
way through all the city.
Umayya and the slave masters
will come for you...
...Bilal.
We must leave.
- Where would we go?
To a great city.
One that welcomes us with open hearts.
HAMZA: Attractive, isn't it?
Men crafted the blade to hunt and...
...provide food for his family.
These days...
...men use it...
...to break each other.
Its true purpose and value...
...has been lost.
BILAL: Will you teach me how to fight?
- Why?
You think if you have wielded a weapon...
...the outcome might've been in your favor...
...or do you seek to take what you desire,
with the sword?
Remember...
...I can only show you how to use it...
...but you alone must decide...
...where and when.
Violence does not always solve disputes.
Do not allow yourself to be lured into a battle...
...you can avoid.
- When do we start?
- As soon as you put back the
sword...
...and pick up that stick.
HAMZA: Saad!
Alright.
Let's try some sparring.
SAAD: Show me what you've got, rookie.
BILAL: Ha! After you 'apple-hunter'.
HAMZA: Turn around!
Duck!
Now parry!
As we practiced, Bilal.
As we practiced!
My, you're not bad Bilal.
Try to dodge this!
BILAL: Ghufaira?
SAAD: Ha! I beat you again.
Come, get up.
Let's spar when you cool down, Bilal.
AL-SIDDIQ: Never stike in anger.
We will free her, Bilal.
Do not lose hope.
He who conquers his anger is strong...
...he who forgives when having the power
to seek revenge...
...will witness glory.
- I promise...
...I will try harder.
- Promise me to train this.
True strength is in the mind, Bilal.
Not in the weapon.
And thats is Hamza's secret.
One day...
...you'll discover your own secret.
# The full moon rose over us, #
# From the valley of Wada'; #
# And it is incumbent upon us to show gratitude, #
# For as long as anyone in existence calls out to Allah. #
(horses neigh)
Hiyaah!
# Oh our Messenger amongst us, #
# Who comes with the exhortations to be heeded; #
# You have brought to this city nobility, #
# Welcome oh you who call us to a good way. #
(children shouts)
(children laughs)
(girl grunts & sighs)
GIRL: Come with me,
we wil take you to your home!
BILAL: (laughs) Wait, where we are going?
(child shouts) Bilal!
Where are you taking me?
BILAL: Mother!
Watch me build the home.
BILAL: Watch us build a house...
...where we can gather...
...to spread hope.
Hope...
...to inspire the hearts of men.
AL-SIDDIQ: He (Muhammad) asks,
that you call out to them...
...Master Bilal.
BILAL: From here...
...I will call them.
MOTHER: Show me.
Show me how your voice
will inspire.
How it will be raised to speak
for justice...
...and equality.
ABU AL-HAKAM: What I feared
is happening, Umayya.
They're growing in strength
and numbers.
Are we to stand here, and do nothing?
SAFWAN: He is right, Father.
When a slave defies his master...
...the world turns upside down!
(whispers) Kill them!
Kill them all!
(whispers) Kill!
UMAYYA: We will begin here...
...tonight!
Assemble a great army to crush each...
...and every place that shelters them.
Let it start at with our own households.
Root them all out...
...and kill them.
(whispers) Kill them all!
(shouts) Open the gate!
- Hamza is back with more refugees!
HAMZA: Magnificent horse.
It followed us on the way back.
Do you know him?
BILAL: I do.
We are old friends. (clicks)
He was once owned by Umayya.
- Hmm. Seems he has escaped his oppression
as well.
Take good care of him.
(man shouts) The old man bring news
from Mecca!
OLD MAN: The persecution...
...grows worse every day.
We've lost so much...
...but we were lucky.
We have escaped!
The ones who remain...
...I fear may soon lose their life.
SOLDIER: A message for you,
from the son Umayya.
BILAL: Ghufaira!
AL-SIDDIQ: Where is Bilal?
HAMZA: He's over there, brother.
MAN: My child!
HAMZA: Where are the rest of you?
- We are the only ones left.
BILAL: Hiyahh!
BILAL: Ghufaira!
Ghufaira!
GUARD: Take him outside!
Follow me!
SLAVE: Please, have mercy!
SOLDIER: The slave! Get him!
- Got him!
SOLDIER: You made a great mistake
coming back here, boy!
- Get him up!
- Where is your God now?
SAFWAN: Wait!
BILAL: Ghufaira...
SAFWAN: Proceed.
SOLDIER: Time to meet your God!
HAMZA: Come!
I am not leaving without you.
Hurry!
(guards shout)
(guard shouts)
One year later...
HAMZA: I knew I would find you here.
I have no words
that can make you feel better.
I can only ask you to
keep your mind clear...
...and your heart, true.
And rest assured...
...God will always be there for
you, Bilal.
I have made this for you.
When you decide to use it...
...remember...
...not to allow the blade
to dictate your choices.
AL-SIDDIQ: *O Lord...*
*All praise and glory belong to you.*
*Upon you we rely...*
*...in both hardship and ease.*
UMAYYA: These fools band together to
overthrow us.
I will lead the attack at the front.
You must watch over the city.
They threaten our control...
...our power.
Do not disappoint me.
AL-SIDDIQ: *Protect us from all evil...*
*...for there is no might,*
*...nor power, except with You.*
(altogether) Amen!
UMAYYA: You must be joking.
ABU AL-HAKAM: Most unfortunate.
SOLDIERS: Look at their strength!
- They are too many!
HAMZA: Stand strong, men!
Have faith.
UMAYYA: Send three of our best here.
First, we destroy their morale...
...then we finish them...
...one by one.
HAMZA: Whatever happens, don't come for us.
Stand your ground!
SOLDIER: Make way!
Make way for Ali!
- Make way for Ali!
UMAYYA: I'm going to enjoy this!
(Okba laughs)
(shouts) Take them down!
UMAYYA: Charge!
- Slay them all!
BILAL: Come on, Hamza!
Move!
HAMZA: Archers!
SAAD: Archers!
BILAL: No!
- Always trust the Lion.
HAMZA: Fire!
SAAD: Fire!
SOLDIER: Fire!
SOHEIB: (laughs) Yes!
HAMZA: (chuckles) Where did that come from?
BILAL: I learnt.
From the best.
UMAYYA: Slave!
BILAL: We are brothers...
...killing brothers!
Put an end to this!
Be the better man.
UMAYYA: (laughs)
You're not my brother, boy!
Show me what you've got!
This is how you treat your master?
Let this be the day...
...I finally put you out of your misery!
- Not today...
...Umayya!
UMAYYA: It's time...
for you to join your sister!
(shouts) The ruler of Mecca has fallen!
- Umayya is no more!
- Send word to the rulers in all of Hijaz!
We must prepare for battle!
- Get Master Safwan!
After them all!
(shouts outside)
AL-SIDDIQ:  *There will be victories.*
*Victories of the mind...*
*...and of the soul.*
* Victories that break the chains...*
*...which bind mankind.*
HAMZA: You did well, little brother.
Al-SIDDIQ:  *Victories that unite us as one.*
*Yet this enemy will not surrender.*
*It will plan...*
*...it will linger in the darkness...*
(whispers) Kill him...
*...waiting for the opportunity...*
*...to strike for our heart.*
*There will be victories...*
*...and there will be losses...*
*...that break our hearts.*
*Hate not, my brothers...*
*...for hate...*
*...is a terrible thing.*
*War awaits us.*
*May the Light prevail.*
MECCA
SAFWAN: Is this how you express your faith, Bilal?
Be finished with this.
BILAL: Why?
Why did you kill her?
Answer me!
SAFWAN: Your answer...
...is right outside the window.
Your faith says a man
is judged by his actions.
And what truer way to measure a man...
...than through what gives.
So there she is...
...my single act morality.
BILAL: Don't let it be your last.
BILAL: Ghufaira!
GHUFAIRA: Bilal! (cries)
KID: Give way, give way!
He's about to call out to Mecca!
(chants & cheers)
MOTHER: What do you want to be when you grow up, Bilal?
# Ooh... Oh, oh #
# Yeah #
# I was running away from myself #
# Had a barrel inside of my head #
# I was lyin' awake in my bed #
# Thinking 'bout all the things that you said #
# But now I'm stronger, I'm so much stronger #
# No more running, not any longer #
# And now I'm stronger, and finally I can say #
# That I'm not afraid... Yeah #
Translation and synchronizing
Ikraam